You're called to create a post-apocalyptic giraffe astronaut.
Generated.
Genghis Khan playing a guitar solo, pixel art.
A man holding a delicious apple...
What's with his hands?
Why can't AI art make hands?
It doesn't matter what AI art model you use.
If you have a man holding a delicious apple
his hands will look weird holding it.
Why is this so hard?
Seems easy enough, right?
We've got this weird situation where AI art instantly make...
Abraham Lincoln dressed like glam David Bowie.
But struggles with a woman holding a cell phone.
This isn't just a weird glitch.
The struggle of AI art with hands
can actually teach you something bigger...
about how AI art works.
I mean, what is so hard about this?
I asked an artist who has taught thousands of people...
how to draw hands from imagination.
Before someone becomes
or starts training to be an artist.
Like officially training.
It's pattern recognition.
You just grow up seeing a whole bunch of hands...
and you start knowing what hands look like.
You learn how things look by living in the world
and recognizing patterns.
An AI is similar but has key differences.
Imagine an AI is like you...
but trapped in a museum from birth.
All the machine has to learn from are the pictures...
and the little placards on the side.
Apple: A red apple on a brown table.
That's like the images it sees from the web
and the descriptions that go with them.
It's similar to how you learn, but locked in that museum.
If you want to understand an apple
you can rotate it in your hand.
You can watch it whenever you want.
If AI wants to understand an apple
it has to find another picture of an apple in the museum.
Pattern recognition has allowed AI and people
to draw decent apples...
but the processes differ.
You start training to become an artist, and now you're like
okay, now I have to learn the rules.
And that's where it becomes very different from how AI is learning.
Artists, in order to draw something complicated
we tend to simplify things into basic forms.
And so when you look at a hand...
you pretty much have the big blocky part of the palm, right?
You have the front, you have the back
and then you have the thickness.
So you can pretty much just make that
into like a square with some thickness to it.
Then an artist can add all the style
and texture and detail they want.
AI works differently.
Look at this hand.
The shapes are bizarre, but the AI has done
a great job showing the light and texture here.
Remember, the AI knows how things look
but not how they work.
So these patterns in pixels are easy to understand.
It never learned, however
that fingers don't really bend like this.
It doesn't simplify the forms.
Remember, it's trapped in the museum
so it is just trying to guess where hand-like pixels should be.
Without knowing how hands work like we do.
But listen, I find this kind of dissatisfying.
I mean, I'm basically just saying that AI can't draw hands
because it's not a person.
But AI also doesn't know anything about construction
and it can still make a beautiful skyscraper
in New York City.
So to understand this better
I spoke to two people who have worked
with generative art models.
Yilun Du is a grad student whose heart is in robotics.
But, you know, AI art is like a big deal now.
So, he got pulled into it.
Because of how popular these models have been
in generative art....
I've also been working on that.
And I talked to Roy Shilkrot
who has a super varied resume
but has been teaching about generative art since 2018.
Good students that come in....
that are trying to break those models
take them to the next level.
Talking to them helped me figure out
three big reasons.
Not every reason, but three big reasons
that hands are tough for AI art models.
The data size and quality
the way hands act and the low margin for error.
For the data size, let's go back to the museum idea.
The museum the robot hangs out in
it has a ton of rooms dedicated to faces...
but not so many rooms for hands.
That means it has less to learn from.
Just as an example, available datasets
like Flickr HQ has 70,000 faces.
70,000.
And this popular one annotates 200,000 pics of celebrity faces...
for lots of details like eyeglasses or pointy noses.
There are a ton of great hand datasets
that can really understand hands
like this one with 11,000 hands.
But these may not have been used to train the AI that makes art.
That data scarcity combines with the quality
and complexity of the data.
Hands data in the art museum
isn't yet annotated to show how they work.
Like the celebrities pointy noses.
What they say is...
there is an image and there is a person in the image
and that person is holding an umbrella.
You don't give the machine a lot of clues
saying this is a person holding the umbrella.
The thumb is going from one side
of the handle and the fingers are curled...
and then thumb is covering the index finger
but not the other one.
All that is made worse because hands do lots of things
compared to, say... faces.
So there's a pretty common like portrait photo face.
There are a lot of these photos online
and the thing is everything is very well centered, right?
Like eyes are always around here.
Like there's always this order.
That's not true of hands which can do this
and this and this.
I swear I'm sober right now.
Stan mentioned this, too.
How many fingers do you see right now?
Like two or three.
Like it doesn't know there's five.
Because sometimes there's two
sometimes there's three
sometimes four, sometimes five.
You can see these problems with AI hands
but the jankiness is all over AI art.
Just look at horses.
You can also have like three legs, five legs, six legs.
The model does not learn to explain this because there's too much diversity
and it doesn't have as much bias as we do.
Okay. Did you hear that last part he said?
Good, because it's really important.
It doesn't have as much bias as we do.
We care a lot about hands and need them to be perfect.
There is a low margin for error.
But because the model doesn't understand hands
hasn't seen many and because hands act weird...
it makes pictures that are like hands it’s seen in the museum
but not an exact hand.
That's good enough for a ton of stuff, but not hands.
Here, let me give you some examples.
Come over here.
So I typed “make me a person with exactly five freckles”.
So this one's from Dall-E 2.
This one is from Stable Diffusion
and this one is from Midjourney.
So it's like, you know, great job.
You've got a red haired person.
They're more likely to have freckles.
But there are not exactly five freckles here.
Here that doesn't really matter because we see a freckly face.
But hands require higher standards.
Look at our apple-holding man again.
I made 3 other variations.
The hands are all weird, but don't look at them right now.
It changed the shirt stripes, the buttons, the apple style...
None of that matters because it's stripe-like
button-like and apple-like.
But hand-like isn't good enough.
I came away from this thinking a couple of things.
AI art is basically bad at art.
We're just able to see it with hands...
and B, it's never going to get any better.
But both of those things are a bit wrong.
I will say that the newest AI art generator to come out
at the time of this video is Midjourney version 5
and they made some progress with hands for sure...
but it's not totally fixed yet.
Don't tell the AI
to hold an umbrella.
I think they're spending lots of time
on some things that you appreciate, which is why you like the images
and a lot of stuff that you don't actually even notice.
I think that for a lot of natural scenery or something like that
I feel like model might be better at that than people.
And they are working on two things.
First, they have the AI look at a ton more pictures
which requires more computing power.
They're trying to solve that on a big scale
because if you want to train
on more than a handful of images...
if you want to train more than 100 images
this would take tremendous resources from you
to retrain the model itself.
The other solution might be to invite more people...
into the museum.
There's an interesting analog.
So like, have you heard of like ChatGPT?
The big difference was that it basically used human feedback.
So like they generated many, many sentences
and asked people to rate which ones are good and which ones are not good.
They basically fine tune the model
so that it would generate sentences
that are convincing to people.
I guess it would require a lot of engineering
to get people to label so much data.
But I think if we could just get like people to rank...
how good the images are generated by these models
then like a lot of these issues will go away, actually.
Because they're just training the models to do what people like.
It's not just the hand... teeth and abs.
Anything where there's like a pattern...
a large amount of something.
It doesn't know the rule of “there are this many”
because it's trained on different amounts.